so hi john uh we're dick price and
sharon kyle from la progressive we've
produced la progressive social justice
magazine for 13 years and we're so glad
that you're uh willing to sit still for
for an interview
my way
to do it thanks for the invitation
great
so by way of introduction for people who
aren't totally familiar with your story
for 14 years you served as a cia
analyst and case officer which included
leading the team that captured
al-qaeda's abu zadata in pakistan in
but then in 2007 three years after you
resigned you became the first cia
officer to publicly acknowledge that as
ci that the cia used torture and its use
was official official policy under the
george w bush administration five years
later in 2012 the obama administration
filed espionage's charges against you
you eventually pled guilty to violating
the intelligence identities protection
act by confirming the name of an officer
involved in the infamous cia rendition
program
sentenced to 30 months in prison you
were released in 2015 after serving
almost two years
and you've written several books about
your various experiences all with great
titles the reluctant spy my secret life
in the cia's war on terror the
convenient terrorists abu zubaydah and
the weird wonderland of america's secret
wars
and doing time like a spy how the cia
taught me to survive and thrive in
prison and then sharon a little bit
later wants to drill into your prison
experiences you also wrote a series of
letters uh entitled letters from loretto
written from the prison in pennsylvania
so uh
as a first question
given that we're we're working on uh
the assange issues what parallels can
you draw from your your treatment by the
us government and its current treatment
of
uh julian assange
i think that the u.s government
specifically the justice department has
learned lessons uh from a string of
whistleblowers and they're not good
lessons you know one of the very first
whistleblowers post dan ellsberg that
the cia and the justice department went
after was tom drake from nsa and they
charged tom with
nine felonies including seven counts of
espionage that case completely fell
apart and they had to drop every one of
those those felony charges
they began
charging um
other whistleblowers in fact just during
the obama administration there were
eight of us that were charged under the
espionage act and each one of those
cases got a little stronger because the
justice department learned from its
previous mistakes and it learned a lot
from the drake case so when it got for
example
to reality winner who uh was an nsa
whistleblower and who was accused
of of leaking
one page of paper
uh a classified analysis on russian
involvement with the trump campaign she
got five and a quarter years
for leaking that one page of paper uh
terry albury an fbi agent in minneapolis
minnesota leaked a barely classified
memo saying that there was systemic
racism in the fbi's
hiring and promotion process and got
three and a half years in prison for
that now this law the the uh espionage
act was written in 1917 to combat german
saboteurs during the first world war
it's never been
meaningfully updated and it was meant to
go after
uh uh spies real spies spies who steal
secrets for foreign countries it was
never meant to be an iron fist against
journalists and against whistleblowers
and that's where julian comes in
this is the first time
uh at least
in the last
75 years that the us government has gone
after a journalist a decorated
journalist in this case
using the espionage
but not just the espionage act they've
enlisted
the help of of allies like the uk and
ecuador and we learned recently spain uh
to spy on him to keep him in what was
essentially a solitary confinement in a
in a situation that niels melser the u.n
special rapporteur on torture calls
torture
and so what the justice department did
to
us whistleblowers they've done in spades
to julian assange and they've coupled
that with especially harsh treatment
so what do you think the consequences
for the public's right to know in
journalism is this throwing a wet
blanket or uh i mean it seems to be
intended to scare the bejesus out of
potential whistleblowers and and in the
case of james and journalists who might
talk to them
yeah a cia officer told
scott shane of the new york times after
my
uh
my incarceration that the point wasn't
to
convict me of a crime it wasn't even to
incarcerate me it was to scare the
daylights out of anybody else who was
considering blowing the whistle on waste
fraud abuse or illegality and scott
shane said that on the day of my arrest
literally all of the new york times
national security sources went silent
and stayed silent for more than six
months
so that really is the point the point is
to frighten people now in the case of
julian it's more than that it's worse
than that because this is a journalist
doing his job as a journalist he's being
prosecuted for journalism so if julian
is found guilty under the espionage act
then what's to keep this administration
or the next one from finding a pulitzer
prize-winning reporter from the new york
times the washington post guilty of
espionage for reporting on national
security this is a very slippery slope
and i i don't think i'm overstating it
by saying that the constitution is in
danger here at least the first amendment
is
so so given that threat to the first
amendment amendment and to journalists
in general why do you think the
mainstream journalists and mainstream
media are generally so quiet about your
case
jeffrey sterling's case julian assange i
mean there are there are good articles i
read a good article in the new yorker
about you but i mean they're few and far
between and and it's a direct threat to
the first amendment and the journalism
why are they quiet
i actually asked a night ritter
journalist why uh he was quiet and he
said because julian assange is an
activist not a journalist
and i said maybe he's an activist but at
the very least he's a publisher and
wikileaks has never had to issue a
correction uh or or apologize for saying
something or publishing something that
was incorrect and certainly the new york
times and the washington post and others
um have
have landed huge scoops based on the
information that julian assange has
published
uh you know i think that there's a root
cause to all this though and that is uh
the demise of investigative journalism
in the united states these big outlets
by and large don't have budgets anymore
for real investigative journalism and so
instead of developing sources inside the
cia or nsa or the fbi they just go to
the office of public affairs
and i know some journalists
who have told me to my face
that
they don't have the time or the money to
develop these journalists they go to the
office of public affairs and the office
of public affairs has threatened them
that if they publish anything that the
cia doesn't like that they will be cut
off forever and they won't have access
to any information anymore and they just
don't want to risk that at this stage of
their careers they're willing just to do
as they're told you know there's another
thing too ken delanian who used to be
a pretty prominent front page reporter
for the los angeles times he's since
moved on to uh nbc and msnbc he was
caught a few years ago sending his
articles to the cia for clearance
before sending them to his own editor we
know that thanks to jason leopold of
buzzfeed who filed a freedom of
information act request and caught ken
delaney in red-handed that's not
journalism uh that's that's fascism uh
to tell you the truth it's
authoritarianism it's bad for our
democracy
so
uh it's reported that you still support
the cia mission generally but you had a
crisis in uh conscious oh that's not
true okay so
i've written extensively on
on the fact that i i don't think that
there ought to be a cia i've said as
recently as a week ago that
the the state department's bureau of
intelligence and research does analysis
that is at least as good as the cias
nsa
has
far superiority over the cia in
technical collection the pentagon's
defense human services
bureau uh
runs
human source
intelligence and so
the cia is redundant there's no reason
to have a cia and then when it with a
track record dating back to 1947 of
of overthrowing governments and
murdering world leaders and interfering
in elections and abusing human rights
i just don't see what good the
organization is there's no reason for it
to be around
so when you um retire retired or when
you left and was it 2004
yes
was it for these reasons
[Music]
in part uh you know when i got back from
from pakistan in 2002 uh
within days of my arrival back at
headquarters i was asked if i wanted to
be trained in the use of what they
called enhanced interrogation techniques
i had never heard that term before and i
asked what it meant and
the the cia officer who
had pitched me explained
what it was and i said man that sounds
like a torture program that can't
possibly be legal
and very excitedly he said we're going
to get rough with these guys and he
claimed that it was legal it had been
approved by the justice department and
by the national security adviser and
signed by the president all of which was
true
well i had a moral and ethical problem
with it besides
being pretty dark uncertain that this
was illegal i don't care what the
justice department said this is illegal
and i can get into details why i believe
that and i turned it down
well
that caused me to have uh
to gain a nickname
the human rights guy and i kind of
chuckled the first time i heard it and
my boss pulled me aside he said buddy
that's not a compliment and then i got
passed over for a promotion
and i had just captured the number three
in al qaeda with with these hands
and i was passed over for promotion
and i went and complained and and was
told look
and these were the exact words that the
head of the cia's counterterrorism
center used that i displayed a shocking
lack of commitment to counter terrorism
because i wouldn't torture up as a beta
now
i like to think i'm a student of history
right i have a deep interest in it
i read constantly
and i knew that in 1946
we executed japanese soldiers who had
waterboarded american prisoners of war
we executed them that was a death
penalty offense
in january of 1968
the washington post ran a front-page
photograph of an american soldier
waterboarding a north vietnamese
prisoner the day that that picture ran
in the post robert mcnamara the infamous
secretary of defense
um ordered an investigation the soldier
was arrested he was convicted of torture
and sentenced to 20 years at leavenworth
well the law never changed
we changed
so why was this a death penalty
offense in 1946 and were there of worthy
of 20 years in prison in 1968 but then
in 2002 no i'd say it's perfectly fine
you can do whatever you want
well
that's not the way the government works
we're supposed to be a nation ruled by
law a nation governed by the rule of law
and so if you want to torture people
then you're going to have to pass the
law saying that it's okay to torture
people because as things stand now
torture is illegal and indeed if someone
at the justice department wanted to
pursue it you can be sentenced to death
for it
that was my objection
one point and then alternatively so
interestingly uh yesterday we saw a play
called our man in santiago
of a delightful play but it's about the
assassination of salvador allende
so sharon has some questions
you bet
yeah i want i my questions are going to
be centered around um your prison
experience
and but first i want to ask you so your
parents immigrated here uh from greece
my grandparents did grandpa
yep
okay and so and you were raised in
sharon pennsylvania
uh yeah in nearby i was born in sharon
and raised in nearby newcastle
pennsylvania so i'm wondering um with
being second generation america american
and coming from the area of the country
that you came from
did you has your sense of america and
our various systems
changed in the past
[Laughter]
wow yes capital y capital e capital s
uh you know western pennsylvania is
it's blue dog country um
everybody's registered democrat and
they're all very conservative pro-labor
pro-life pro-gun uh it was very heavily
amish country
so i grew up out in the styx
and um
my my grandparents were so grateful to
be in this country
and instilled in us such a sense of
gratefulness that i only considered
public service i didn't even think i
didn't even consider
going into you know business or banking
or whatever i don't even know what i
would do um
outside of public service and then when
this position at the cia present itself
you know the cia
pitched me i i didn't apply to the cia
um
i i saw it as a way to serve my country
and a way to see the world which i
really really wanted to do and i sought
out
a friend of a friend um i had a a friend
in grad school whose boyfriend worked
for the cia
and um
she's she set up a dinner for us because
i had questions about human rights to
tell you the truth
and so um we had dinner in dc one night
and he assured me
that um
things had changed with the church
commission those changes had stuck
uh those battle days were behind us
blah blah blah you're gonna have a great
experience there and i thought okay and
i was naive i was what
23 years old
and
and so
i accepted the job
and then bill clinton became president
and sure enough
the agency initiated something called a
cull
where they went through the files of
literally every
source who had been recruited and if any
source had a problem with human rights
in his or her background they were um
they were fired
uh we used the word terminated but
people are gonna
make too much of that
they were just fired and told that we
just can't work with them anymore fully
one-third
of the cia's recruited assets were fired
in that call and i remember saying to a
colleague wow
bill clinton is serious about human
rights i got to tell you how happy i am
about this i think i really made the
right decision here
and that held until september 11 2001
and things not just changed but changed
to the point where we crossed a rubicon
and there's no going back
not
until
some point
when members of the congressional
oversight committees
decide that their job really does
include oversight you know frank church
is dead otis pike is dead ted kennedy is
dead
and no one really took their places
ideologically
and so instead of oversteers on capitol
hill we have committees that are made up
of little more than cheerleaders i
confronted ron wyden the democratic
senator from oregon when i got home from
prison
and um i said you know senator i i
frankly expected a little bit more
support from you and he got very angry
and he said look
it takes all of my energy just to not
lose my security clearance
and i thought wow so that's what it's
about they even control ron wyden
all they have to do is threaten him say
something we don't like and we're going
to take your security clearance and how
in the world are you going to serve on
the oversight committee without a
security clearance
so
my position right now is that there's no
hope of reform at the cia it can't be
reformed because it has so protected
itself bureaucratically that no one from
the outside can change it
interesting interesting so your time in
prison clearly
based on my readings of your letters i
gave you a deeper understanding of the
so-called uh u.s correctional system
right um for those who haven't read any
of your letters do you want to talk
about well for example your last letter
where you you list 19 different things
that you won't miss
about
prison and i thought it was somewhat
striking that of those 19
it seemed to me that every single one of
them had to do with staff with the
exception of the pedophiles
um yeah
yeah i don't miss the pedophiles
yeah uh one of the things that i that i
learned
very very quickly was the problem in
prison and the danger in prison is from
staff
look
the truth is and this is an ugly truth
but the bureau of prisons is really
nothing more than an employment agency
for
otherwise
unemployable
under educated uh
[Music]
yes these prisons are in the place where
the nearest town is this is oftentimes
the only employer in town and if you're
somebody who has gotten out of the
military
and got thrown out of the police academy
or just couldn't cut it in the police
academy where else are you going to work
where else are you going to work where
the only qualifications are a ged and no
felony convictions that's literally the
only qualifications to be a prison guard
in the federal bureau of prisons
seriously
a ged and no felony convictions
and then you know you give people
a badge and a stick and you've created a
monster
a monster that that was one thing that i
learned very very quickly another thing
you know everybody knows this joke that
you know everybody's in everybody in
prison is innocent right
i was shocked at the number of people
that i would have concluded were
innocent
or
people who were guilty of some minor
crime
and then drew
sentences
you know for example
um
i had been in prison about a year
and
a new prisoner showed up um in the
visitor room and the only reason i
noticed him was that he was covered in
tattoos from his neck
to his toes his hands even the palms of
his hands completely totally covered in
tattoos
he turned out to be a very nice guy and
he was from right there in the area he
he was born and raised within 20 miles
of the prison
and every single weekend his wife would
come with their four daughters
little girls like between 5 and 12.
and they loved their dad and they would
take turns sitting on his lap and he he
was so kind to them and sweet to them
so finally one day i went up to him and
introduced myself
and um in the course of conversation i
asked him
do you mind if i ask you what you're in
for
and he said yeah i got caught i got
caught
uh taking a car load of weed from
pennsylvania to ohio
he he ran a a heating and air
conditioning business that he had built
himself it wasn't doing well
most of the houses in pennsylvania don't
have air conditioning it's not hot
enough
and so um
he thought he'd make some extra money by
taking a little bit of weed across the
state line well that's a federal crime
and it's and it's uh transportation
they gave him 20 years in prison
20 years so not only
does he have the obvious cost of not
watching his girls grow up they're all
going to be married and gone by the time
he gets out of prison
but the government's actions put a dozen
people out of work he employed a dozen
people
and
i had to ask rhetorically
is society better off
with him locked up in a cage
are we safer as a country with him in a
cage
it just doesn't make any sense to me now
the pedophiles i understand the
pedophiles are dangerous right and i i
met you know a serial killer i met a
contract killer there are a lot of bad
dangerous people who need to be
in prison
but but people in on drug sentences i
mean i know it would be a mammoth
undertaking but honestly i feel like
every single person in america who is in
prison on a drug charge should have a
sentence review because this is
ridiculous
you know i'll fall back on these very
well-known statistics that the
washington post published we have five
percent of the world's population here
in the united states and we have 25
percent of the world's prison population
and there is no justification for that
whatsoever i i did my own little study
for a piece that i wrote a couple of
years ago and i found that congress
creates 50 new crimes every year not
laws
they don't pass 50 new laws they create
50 new felonies
every single year they've done this for
the last 20 years where a year ago
there was some action that was perfectly
legal that this year is a felony that is
a thousand new felonies in the last 20
years
this is an excuse
we can't continue living like this it's
not
absolutely
wow
so um
the letters that you wrote were so open
and honest
did you i mean based on knowing thank
you that your your your letters were
read
you know by the staff
did you fear retribution
i mean they didn't die
thank you you know it all started as an
accident
um one of my attorneys jessalyn radak
uh the day that i left
uh for prison she said to me look when
you get on your feet and you feel
comfortable
send me a letter and i'll circulate it
among there were like 600 people that
had signed up for a mailing list that
just wanted to know how i was doing so i
said okay
so
about six weeks later i felt all right i
feel like i know what i'm doing here
i'm gonna write a letter and just tell
everybody i'm doing fine and tell them
what some of the experiences are like so
i wrote
that first what i called letter from
loretto and i did to honor martin luther
king and his uh letter from birmingham
jail
so um
so i wrote this thing
and
i gave two i told two stories i gave two
examples of staff malfeasance
not thinking that people don't do that
right you don't call out staff
so i called them out
and um and i sent it to jessalyn and she
put it on the mailing list but i didn't
know that jessalyn was friends with
ariana huffington
and so she sent it to ariana who put it
like this banner headline on the
huffington post and it went completely
crazy i got two million hits that first
week i ended up giving interviews to
jake tapper came um came to the prison
to interview me and i gave an interview
to playboy and npr and the atlantic
monthly and
oh my god i can't even remember but it
it went everywhere all the three
broadcasts the four broadcast networks
and cnn fox and msnbc it just went
everywhere
and
i could tell one day like people are
looking at me and you know giving me the
thumbs up and i'm like yeah okay
but that thought that was weird
and then finally one of the guards the
female guard pulled me aside and she
said have i ever been rude to you
and i said no
i i don't think we've ever had any
interaction so you're not talking about
me in that thing i said what thing
and she said that letter you wrote i
said the letter from loretto she said
yes i said how have you seen that
and she says everybody in america has
seen it
i said what are you talking about
and so she allowed me into the guard
booth
and showed me on the internet and i
thought oh my god
but
and of course i get called to the
warden's office and he wants to know the
names of the of the guards and i said
what you want me to do your job for you
now too i said i'm not a rat
i said you know let me have my my to
speak my piece but i'm not ratting
anybody out i never used any names never
and so um
the more i thought about it the more
that i realized that
if i could remain
that public
it would protect me from them
because they knew that i had access to
the media you know it's funny one of the
things that i did after i had been there
about six months
um
sorry i'm just checking the gate i keep
getting these texts saying that we're
boarding and we're not boarding
so
i don't go no no
one of the things that i did after i'd
been there about six months was to file
a freedom of information act request on
myself with the bureau of prisons just
out of curiosity and i got back about uh
200 pages and 90 of it was garbage it
was just my visitors list and my health
records and stuff like that but then
there were about six pages that were
clearly marked at the top and the bottom
of each page
foia exempt do not release to inmate so
either they're so stupid in the freedom
of information act office that they
can't read
or somebody took pity on me
and decided that i had a right to see
this stuff
so what it was was it was it was memos
from the warden to the staff before i
got there
warning them that i had access to the
media and one of them was just it was
one sheet and in these huge block
letters it said warning
inmate has access to the media
and so uh yeah and so i realized that
that they were far more afraid of me
than i was of them
um they did try to shut me down a couple
of times they tried to rip my desk off
the wall but i had heard a rumor that
they were going to do it so i paid a guy
a bag of tuna fish to strip the the
screws and sure enough two hours later
they came and tried to yank it off and
they just couldn't get their drill to
to uh get the screws out
and um
there were a couple that i had to
smuggle
i had to smuggle out which was a little
bit difficult that drove them crazy but
you know most of those letters
all i did was i just put them in an
envelope and sent them
that was it
um i would send one to my lawyer
in legal mail which they're not allowed
to search they're not allowed to search
anything you send to a journalist
so i would send one to
uh jane hampshire at uh shadow proof it
used to be called firedoglake.com
one to my lawyer one to my wife
um one to my publisher because i wanted
to turn it into a book later and so
they just couldn't figure out how i was
getting them out
and i allowed them to think that i had
this sophisticated smuggling operation
going in fact i was just put an envelope
and put a stamp on it and sent it
wow so it's sort of ironic it appears
that
the systems of of corruption within the
prison system
almost paralleled what was going on at
the cia in terms of not wanting the
media you know not wanting to put light
on what's
oh yeah the the parallels were striking
they really were i mean at a
jv kind of level
but um
but yeah you know we've got the uh
commissary right the commissary has an
across-the-board 30 markup
and that 30
is supposed to be used to buy athletic
equipment
books for the library things like that
well instead and i know this because i
filed a freedom of information act
request instead they took the thirty
percent
um we didn't get any
athletic equipment or books for the
library and instead it bought them
workout equipment and a large screen tv
for the for the guards lounge
well you know what that's illegal
you can't do that
uh but that kind of petty corruption is
is a way of life there one one guard got
caught that they fired him he deserved
it he got caught um he just backed up
his
pickup truck to the commissary and
loaded a thousand dollars worth of
groceries into the back of his pickup
truck and just drove home
you you can't do that
you know that's grand theft
so
so early in this interview you talked
about how the cia is um it's redundant
and it shouldn't exist how do you feel
about the prison abolition movement
uh i support a lot of what the prison
abolition movement um stands for i i do
not support the complete abolition of
prisons i i learned that there are some
very very dangerous
people in prison
there are people with severe untreatable
mental illness
psychosis
anti-social personality disorders there
are a lot of sociopaths and psychopaths
people who are genuinely dangerous
but
you know why does no other country have
the same kind of
car cereal problems that we do
why does no other country have the kind
of recidivism that we do
you know look if you take a guy
out of some terrible neighborhood
and you charge him with a drug crime and
you put him in prison for 10 years or 15
or 20 years
you provide him no programming
you don't teach him to be a plumber or a
mechanic or an electrician
and then you let him out
what do you think he's gonna do
he's gonna go back and do the only thing
that he knows how to do
because you didn't teach him anything
else
so that's why we have the recidivism
rates that we have because
we do these people wrong
by not helping them to improve their
lives what better opportunity you have
literally a captive audience what better
opportunity to give someone a marketable
skill and help them turn their lives
around and the prison system doesn't do
that
uh i i really have come to believe
i mean i was never a supporter of the
so-called war on drugs but but now i
feel like i have a a rich understanding
of just how wrong
and dangerous this this awful policy has
been
yeah it's it's
it's so it's paralyzing crippling to our
society
you know when one out of every four
black men is on parole probation or in
prison
you've got a problem and the problem's
not crime
the problem is a policy problem
but nobody wants to talk about that
right because those people have been
labeled
um disregardable
what's happened to you exactly and what
happened to you when you were given the
label of a but the human rights person
first you're labeled yeah it's okay to
just do whatever to you
yep isn't that the truth there was a guy
that i was there with
um i i was warned about him
in advance he was he was very dangerous
and he was a serial killer
um
the story was that he had killed 14
women
he was a long long-distance truck driver
and he was killing prostitutes at truck
stops along his route this was in the
1970s before the use of dna
and so
he picked up a 16 year old prostitute
and raped her and strangled her and
threw her into a ditch on the side of
the road thinking that she was dead but
she wasn't and she recovered and she
identified him
the police knew that he was the serial
killer but they just couldn't prove it
so they got him on the rape charge and
um and he got 20 years
um
he got out after doing the 20 years at a
state facility in colorado
and
the cops and the prosecutors
were afraid that he was going to start
killing people again so they sort of set
him up
they harassed him at home
with with unannounced visits and
inspections of his house
until finally he got so angry that he
punched his parole officer well they
found a gun in his house there's a
mandatory minimum sentence of eight
years for being a felon with a gun uh
they got him for assault on a federal
officer he ended up with another 20
years so um
even though he was never convicted of of
any of the murders 40 years in prison is
enough to make people feel
safer
uh
he ended up going to a higher security
prison because
well it was because i set him up to tell
you the truth i was a little bit afraid
of this guy everybody was afraid of him
for whatever reason that i never
understood he actively sought my
approval
um he would say you know hey john i
saved you a seat in the tv room to watch
the game today okay thanks truck
um hey john there's a new classic rock
station at uh 16 10 a.m
appreciate it truck
well one day
there was a guy that had been giving me
problems
uh he was a contract killer
and um and was doing 20 to life for
murdering
a businessman in pittsburgh
and so uh
so this guy wanted to move into my into
my room and i i said i was in i was
uncomfortable with his crime
i said i don't want any pedophiles in my
room and i don't want any contract
killers so tash
so you know the guards would at least
let us have a vote if somebody wanted to
move into our into our cell
so we voted no and he was furious well
one day i got a i got called to the
lieutenant's office because npr had
requested an interview and i had to go
down and sign a waiver allowing the
interview
and i'm sitting next to truck in the tv
room and this contract killer
he's standing like three feet away from
me i'm right behind him and he just
didn't see me he's standing at the email
computers
and he says to the guy next to him hey
did you hear kiriakou got
got called down to the lieutenant's
office
and the guy said yeah and the contract
killer says
that guy's a rat he went down there to
rat us out well
if you call somebody a rat blood's gonna
be spilled
so i'm sitting there like this in the
chair and truck says to me
did you hear that
that guy just called you a rat
like what are you gonna do about it and
i said to truck
an hour ago i heard him call you a
pedophile
[Laughter]
totally untrue
without saying a single word he got up
and he beat that guy into a coma
yeah into a coma
and so truck got another five years onto
his
40. and was shipped to a medium security
prison they upgraded him
and this contract killer
he was in the hospital for several weeks
and then he was in solitary confinement
for a few weeks after that finally he
came back
and a couple guys told him what i had
done
and so he walked up to me and he still
had like visible
injuries
and he says very meekly i want to
apologize for calling you a rat i should
never have done that
and i'm sorry it won't happen again and
i said to him very quietly this is what
i learned in prison
i said if i ever hear
my name
cross your lips
ever again
you're dead
do you understand
and he just said yes like this
and you know what i never had to lift a
finger
and i let truck do my dirty work and
everybody saw what happened
and so nobody messed with me
they already saw that the guards didn't
mess with me
and now they didn't mess with me either
so
so julian assange is still
um
his extradition is still pending
largely
because of the state of our
here in the united states yes
yes and you know the european court of
human rights has has twice ruled against
the extradition of other prisoners
that the u.s was seeking one on drug
charges and one on an international
fraud charge but our prison system is so
well known for its decrepit state and
for our weaponized use of solitary
confinement
that the european uh court of human
rights won't extradite people that's why
i can't imagine even though even though
we've already gone through brexit i
can't imagine that a court of appeals
would extradite julian especially now in
light of two things number one is
the reporting from um mike isikoff at
newsweek that
the cia had made plans to kill julian or
to snatch him and two
uh because
the fbi's
sole source is a convicted pedophile and
fraudster
who has admitted
to making up half of what he told the
fbi
i mean no judge in his right mind
would agree to extradite somebody based
on that i i can't even believe and this
is one of the real disappointments for
me with the bide administration i can't
believe biden just hasn't walked away
from this
what you you want another humiliating
defeat just walk away from this it's all
over yeah it's it's just it's so strange
that he's even pursuing it especially
since obama the obama administration
didn't
exactly right
so about the issagoff yahoo piece uh
based on your experience was that
surprising to you or is that uh running
the mills it's not surprising
no that that's what they do there
there's a very very clear um
um
way to
conceptualize and have approved a covert
action program somebody comes up with an
idea
uh there's there's a staff that handles
this kind of thing and what they do is
they put it all in the right format put
it in the right memo and then they send
it to the justice department's office of
legal counsel olc that's where john you
and jay bybee were
um during the the battle days of torture
in the bush administration well olc will
stand on its head
to
come up with its own memo saying that
the proposal is legal under u.s law
and then
after negotiating language back and
forth with their cia counterparts it
goes to the national security council
general council
and so
the nsc's lawyers then work with the
cia's lawyers to come up with all the
right legal language and then it goes to
the national security advisor for
the final
well the panel ultimate signature if the
national security advisor signs it then
it goes to the president in the form of
a presidential finding which is a
different template and then the
president signs the finding so this is
where it broke down and i'm surprised
this is this has not been generally
reported but to me this is the important
part
it made its way through olc
it made its way through all the lawyers
but it never made its way to the
president
because donald trump never had a chance
to sign it which tells me that h.r
mcmaster said are you people insane
we're not going to do this and he killed
it
that's why julian's still alive today
because at least one person in the trump
white house hadn't lost his marbles yet
and put an end to it to me that's the
real story
so
the last question from me uh at great
risk to yourself and loss of uh business
opportunities and end of a career
i mean you you took a stand do you think
you and other whistleblowers have taken
stands do you think it has changed
anything about the policies or if the
cia is just chugging along with the same
old old programs it's done for 60 years
that's a good question
um and you know we have to
we have to judge i think based on
incremental changes
um
at first glance i would say
you know i hate to admit but we really
haven't affected much change
but that wouldn't really be
true
um first of all
i was greatly greatly heartened
in december 2013
when ed snowden told
the new york times that tom drake and i
inspired him to go
public with his revelations traveling to
new york jfk on those flight 5776
just a few more minutes i'm going to
start our boarding process we're going
to board soon sorry
through the boarding door as well as
throughout your travels with us once we
begin we'll start with passengers
needing extra time more assistance after
which we'll invite our us active duty
military with id
followed by our first class diamond only
360. sorry once again on to our comfort
plus
our sky priority
our main cabinet one two three and
finally
our
finally our basic economy
you're allowed one carry-on and one
personal item any more than two items we
have to please consolidate otherwise
we'll have to check the remainder beyond
that number to your final destination
we're in need of about 15 to 20
passengers to check your bag to your
final destination compliments of delta
we will not be able to accommodate all
of the bags in the overhead bin so if
you're willing to do so please see me at
this time with your bag along with your
boarding pass
we'll check your bag
i would talk over him but i'm afraid it
would wreck your uh recording
we don't get enough volunteers we'll
have to mandatorily check toward the end
of boarding
thank you for your time
um
but ed snowden told the new york times
in december of 2013 that tom drake and i
had inspired him to go public with his
revelations
that in and of itself to me was worth it
but even better than that
once he made his revelations
and granted it's taken several years
public opinion has turned
to the point where
many americans
objects to being spied upon by
government agencies
and little by little members of congress
are coming around to voting the right
way on some of these patriot act uh
provisions so we're not there yet
and it's very very slow but we're
getting there and to me that's all worth
it in in my own case in the case of the
torture program the the benefits were
were far better you know i blew the
whistle in 2007 the torture program was
finally outlawed in what was it 2000
summer of 2015
with the mccain-feinstein amendment and
john mccain said on the floor of the
senate that had i not said anything that
the legislation would never have been
possible so it was worth it
wow well thank you so much you know um
thank you
i i good to meet you both yeah i mean i
regret that you had to spend time behind
behind bars
thank you um it feels great that you've
taken a terrible situation and turned it
into a mechanism for lightning so many
people you know people in the black
community of course you can you can see
that the people in the black community
are disproportionately
impacted
by absolutely right
so
many if not most of us have a deep
understanding of it
but yes america it has to be changed it
has to be the whole situation is
untenable
you can't lock up everybody this was
fabulous john we deeply appreciate it
thank you we're going to use this
question
we're going to use it with our defend
the signs piece and we're going to also
write an article about it here in the
coming days in the la progressive
wonderful so have a safe thank you
thanks so much
i appreciate it i'll talk to you both
soon
alrighty goodbye
oh